<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The benefit of afflictions. By Edward Reynell Esqu.</title>
            <author>Reynell, Edward, 1612-1663.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 68 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91726</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1217</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1914_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209996</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868838</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868838</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170556</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91726)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170556)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 237:E1914[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The benefit of afflictions. By Edward Reynell Esqu.</title>
                  <author>Reynell, Edward, 1612-1663.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 35, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Abel Roper at the Sun in Fleet-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible --  Study and teaching --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170556:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Benefit OF AFFLICTIONS.</p>
            <p>BY <hi>EDWARD REYNELL</hi> Eſqu.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Tim. 2.12.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>If we ſuffer, we ſhall alſo reign with him.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Abel Roper</hi> at the <hi>Sun</hi> in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet,</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:170556:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170556:2"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough this ſmall <hi>Tract,</hi> ſeem not to invite an <hi>Epiſtle,</hi> yet [being faln into an <hi>Age,</hi> wherein Pride, Prejudice and Precipitancy have ſhut our <hi>Eares] I</hi> thought fit to acquaint thee <hi>(Courteous Reader)</hi> that the many raſh and uncharitable Cenſures, ſo frequently
<pb facs="tcp:170556:3"/>vented from the mouths of many [vulgar <hi>Juſtice,</hi> ever judging thoſe <hi>criminous,</hi> whom they ſee <hi>calamitous</hi>] hath oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion'd theſe enſuing <hi>Lines;</hi> as alſo, for the comfort of <hi>thoſe,</hi> whom God (through his <hi>afflicting</hi> hand) ſhall leave <hi>labouring</hi> under the <hi>Pangs</hi> of the worlds <hi>Reproach</hi> and Contempt.</p>
            <p>Nothing being <hi>[now adayes]</hi> more uſual, with the Community of people [the chiefeſt part of whoſe <hi>Innocency</hi> conſiſts in finding <hi>fault</hi> with ſuch as are better then <hi>themſelves]</hi> then to account thoſe the greateſt <hi>ſinners,</hi> who are the deepeſt <hi>Sufferers;</hi> not knowing that the ſoul of every <hi>Saint</hi> conſiſts of ſacred <hi>Riddles</hi> and holy contradictions; and that God makes his chiefeſt <hi>Cordials</hi> out of thoſe <hi>poiſonous</hi> Serpents that <hi>ſting</hi> us: yea, often <hi>extracts</hi> his beſt Antidotes, from what may ſeem to <hi>deſtroy</hi> us.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:170556:3"/>
Which ſhould ſerve to ſilence the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, and clear up the <hi>ſight</hi> of thoſe [whoſe beſt <hi>Objects</hi> ſeem evil, if be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held with <hi>blood-ſhotten eyes</hi>] that make the preſent ſufferings of many, the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est <hi>Indications</hi> of their ſins, and <hi>Gods Juſtice</hi> attending them.</p>
            <p>Neither is it any ſufficient <hi>Argument,</hi> that becauſe God puniſheth our <hi>Faults,</hi> he hates our <hi>perſons:</hi> it being <hi>formerly</hi> the groſs miſtake of thoſe <hi>Heathens, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiſts, and Idolaters,</hi> with the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, and <hi>Hereticks</hi> of old, who fond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly miſtook the meaning of thoſe hot and ſharp <hi>Perſecutions,</hi> which often befell the Primitive Chriſtians, and Orthodox <hi>Profeſſors</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> crucified: conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that they moſt deſerved the true <hi>Croſs,</hi> who ſo much gloried in the <hi>Croſs</hi> of their <hi>Saviour:</hi> no way conſidering that we have often times more cauſe to
<pb facs="tcp:170556:4"/>bleſs God for our <hi>Croſſes,</hi> then our <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorts:</hi> ſeeing, as there is a <hi>Croſs</hi> in the <hi>beſt things</hi> to the <hi>wicked:</hi> ſo there is a <hi>A bleſſing</hi> hidden in the <hi>worſt things</hi> to the <hi>godly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Bue we find it no new <hi>thing,</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn the <hi>Generation of Gods people:</hi> the <hi>Tenents</hi> of <hi>Religion,</hi> which is <hi>myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal and ſpiritual,</hi> being <hi>Paradoxes</hi> to to <hi>carnal men.</hi> If the <hi>Rabble</hi> may have their <hi>Vote,</hi> St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who would not have wanted his <hi>whippings</hi> to have miſsed his <hi>Comforts,</hi> ſhall be accounted <hi>mad, &amp; not fit to live,</hi> Act. <hi>22.22. John Baptiſt</hi> ſhall be accuſed <hi>to have a Devil: The Apoſtles to be full of new wine:</hi> Nay, <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf ſhall be thought, <hi>to be beſides himſelf,</hi> and worthy to be <hi>cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſurely, if every one ſhall adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb facs="tcp:170556:4"/>to read and interpret his <hi>own mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> according to his <hi>Fanatick,</hi> if not prejudicate and malicious <hi>Conjectures,</hi> and the various <hi>Diſpenſations</hi> of Gods <hi>Providence:</hi> extorting the utmoſt of our <hi>Belief,</hi> only to their own ſenſe, and to flatter their own <hi>Party, Opinion, Paſſion</hi> and <hi>Intereſt,</hi> how many ſhould we have ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificed to the <hi>Fury</hi> of <hi>vulgar Zeal,</hi> there being none more hot, and <hi>cenſorious,</hi> than Perſons <hi>profligatae vitae, ac famae,</hi> of egregious <hi>Ignorance,</hi> and profligate Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudence, and void of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> as well as <hi>Modeſty:</hi> who think it no <hi>ſin,</hi> to take away our <hi>Crutches,</hi> and beat us for going <hi>lame:</hi> to make us <hi>Sufferers,</hi> and then load us with <hi>Reproach;</hi> being firſt <hi>injurious,</hi> and then <hi>cenſorious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides, <hi>Proſperity</hi> and <hi>Succeſs</hi> are the great <hi>Idols</hi> of the <hi>Time:</hi> and many ſeem (with eaſe) to trample upon thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:170556:5"/>
               <hi>gods,</hi> whoſe <hi>hands,</hi> they have cut off: not wiſely conſidering the <hi>Paradoxes</hi> of Gods <hi>Providence,</hi> and the depth of his <hi>divine Judgements:</hi> whereby through the <hi>malice</hi> of <hi>men,</hi> and the <hi>fury</hi> of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan,</hi> for the <hi>Tryals</hi> of our <hi>Graces,</hi> and the exerciſe of our <hi>Patience,</hi> he often laies on great <hi>Afflictions,</hi> as well on his whole <hi>Church,</hi> as particular <hi>perſons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And may we ſtill learn in all worldly <hi>mutations,</hi> as well to <hi>kiſs,</hi> as <hi>acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> that <hi>divine hand</hi> [thus guided by the moſt wiſe <hi>Counſel</hi> and <hi>Providence</hi> of a mercifull God, for our <hi>Good</hi>] and to make a wiſe <hi>Improvement</hi> of all our <hi>Croſſes,</hi> whereby to have Recourſe to <hi>Virtue,</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> and our <hi>ſelves:</hi> who becauſe he would not have us periſh here, ſends us <hi>Afflictions</hi> in the world, and by the world as <hi>exemplary</hi> Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb facs="tcp:170556:5"/>in all our <hi>Sufferings:</hi> which, without the <hi>Furnaces</hi> of <hi>Gods Afflictions,</hi> the <hi>worlds Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution,</hi> and the <hi>Devils Temptations</hi> would grow dull and ruſty.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:170556:6"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170556:6"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>UR firſt Encounters with <hi>Life,</hi> are <hi>Tears</hi> and Bonds; and the next Leſſon we are afterwards to learn, is to take up our <hi>Croſs,</hi> and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him, whoſe whole life, was a Life of ſuffering from the <hi>Cradle</hi> to the <hi>Grave,</hi> and from his <hi>Birth</hi> to his <hi>Burial.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Deſarts</hi> and <hi>Mountains</hi> were the Schools of the <hi>Prophets,</hi> and wild honey the diet of <hi>Him,</hi> who (by the Teſtimony of the Son of God) was the greateſt of thoſe that were born of women. They loved their <hi>Sack-cloth,</hi> more then their <hi>Silks,</hi> and the <hi>watching</hi> of their <hi>Body,</hi> was the <hi>Sleep</hi> of their Soul. Neither was there any ſtop between them and heaven in the pouring out of their mournfull ſpeeches, and wreſtling Prayes; and though no day aroſe without its <hi>Cloud,</hi> yet did they no way value the blowes and frownes of a ſtormy world, having once attain'd the true <hi>Olympus,</hi> whoſe <hi>Ayr</hi> was ſo calm and clear.</p>
            <p>It was well ſaid of a School-<hi>Divine, That the Tears of the righteous, were the ſmiles of their ſoul.</hi> When the <hi>Marble</hi> weeps, it waſheth away the <hi>Duſt.</hi> In our chiefeſt ſorrow (which ſhould be for ſin) is healing; penitential <hi>Tears</hi> being the <hi>oyl</hi> of the Sanctuary: why then ſhould we make it our ſtudy to ſhun that ſorrow, which will ſave us from
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170556:7"/>deſtroying? As <hi>Pliny</hi> calls <hi>Sickneſs,</hi> the <hi>Sum of Philoſophy</hi> [if we could but perform that in our health, which we then promiſe] So <hi>Afflictions</hi> are the beſt <hi>Remedy,</hi> to make us know our <hi>ſelves,</hi> when we are in the full <hi>Career</hi> of worldly Pompe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Stars</hi> never ſhine more glorious, then when they are near <hi>Dark Clouds:</hi> Without <hi>Afflictions</hi> and Tryals, God will not be <hi>familiar</hi> with us. Thoſe Trees which are not pruned, will firſt leave to bear, and then <hi>die.</hi> Yea, Nature it ſelf, would decay and periſh, if not dreſſed, and purified by the ſame hand that firſt made her. He that is not favoured with <hi>Croſſes</hi> and Viſitations, is (by St. <hi>Paul</hi>) ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted no Heir of the heavenly <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Diſeaſes,</hi> we know not the benefit of a <hi>Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian;</hi> and God often uſeth to viſit us with his cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections, that he himſelf may become a <hi>Cordial. Before I was afflicted I went a ſtray</hi> (ſaith that Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Prophet) And ſure there is none of Gods <hi>Rods</hi> that we can well want. The waters of <hi>Betheſda</hi> healed not untill the <hi>Angel</hi> had ſtirred them; and though worldly <hi>Tears</hi> be the waters of <hi>Marah,</hi> yet there is a Tree to ſweeten them.</p>
            <p>Thus are we chatechiz'd for <hi>Eternity;</hi> 'tis that which all the Fathers ſo often inculcate; 'tis that which all the Saints have found the benefit of. Gods houſe of <hi>Correction</hi> was their School of <hi>Inſtruction.</hi> The juſteſt man [then alive] was fought againſt <hi>by his Terrors, Job</hi> 6.4. <hi>He that walked before him in truth, and with a perfect heart, had his bones broken by the anger of the Almighty,</hi> Iſa, 38.13. Yea, the man after Gods own heart, was ſo waſted with
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170556:7"/>grief, as that, <hi>His moiſture was turned into the drought of ſummer,</hi> Pſal. 32.3, 4. Nay, his own ſon [though without ſin] muſt bleed upon the <hi>Croſs,</hi> and thoſe whom he hath choſen for himſelf, be tryed in the Furnace of <hi>Affliction, Iſa.</hi> 48.10.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Dung-hill</hi> of this world, will annoy thee, while thou dwelleſt in this <hi>houſe of clay.</hi> The juſt have not only an <hi>Egypt</hi> of <hi>ſin</hi> to encounter with, but <hi>Iſrael</hi> even in <hi>Canaan</hi> is not in reſt. Nay, our Saviour himſelf, firſt taſted the bitter <hi>Gall</hi> of the unmercifull <hi>Croſs,</hi> before he eat of the <hi>Hony-comb.</hi> It is thus that our <hi>Sorrows</hi> muſt be turned into <hi>Sweets.</hi> The corn is not ſeparated but by threſhing, nor men drawn nearer to heaven by worldly impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments ſo much as by tribulation.</p>
            <q>Acriora Orexim excitant embammata.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>Sharp Sauces beget good Appetites;</hi> and the <hi>Thorns</hi> (at laſt prove <hi>Roſes,</hi> in the ſame place, where <hi>inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence</hi> hath ſighed ſo much.</p>
            <p>But oh! how baſely do we ſtartle at every trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble? How do we endeavour to dry up thoſe Tears, before they have ſufficiently cleanſed our filthineſs? whereas <hi>Afflictions</hi> ſhould not be reſiſted, but with great <hi>Pre-caution.</hi> What part ſoever God hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed us, we muſt be contented to act it faithfully. If it be long, it is uſually light; if grievous, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not laſt, <hi>Dies dolorem minuit, time will wear it out;</hi> we can never looſe our ſelves in the pure and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent <hi>Tracts</hi> of vertue. <hi>Grave nihil eſt homini, quod fert neceſſitas,</hi> that which is neceſſary cannot be any way burthenſom.</p>
            <p>Beſides, It is Gods <hi>Prerogative,</hi> and not <hi>thine,</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:170556:8"/>to chuſe thy condition; whither to be ſick or heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy; a mourner, or afflicted. Is it his pleaſure to to make thee the Drunkards <hi>Song,</hi> or a Reproach to <hi>Abjects;</hi> envy not thoſe <hi>Shimeis,</hi> which thus rail on thee, conſidering whoſe doing it is; bite not the ſtone, but look unto him that throwes it; keep cloſe to thy <hi>Station,</hi> and thou ſhalt find no ſmall comfort at laſt; patience will digeſt thy miſery. Sure all is not loſt; after a little forbearance, we ſhall come out from theſe vapours of <hi>Calumnie,</hi> as the <hi>Sun</hi> out of a <hi>Cloud</hi> at noon-day.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Afflictions</hi> of man (I confeſs) are more moving then of any other creature, for he only is a ſtranger here. All things elſe are at home: but <hi>Ardua florifera Crux, The painfull Croſs ſhall at laſt be crowned with Palms and Flowers.</hi> A joyfull <hi>heart</hi> will (at laſt) prove the fruit of his <hi>innocence,</hi> though grief and ſorrow be the <hi>Bud and Prim-roſe</hi> thereof; our <hi>Manſion</hi> is in heaven, where our <hi>Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our</hi> is gone to prepare a place for us.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Martyrs</hi> were wont to mitigate their pain, with the thought of <hi>home,</hi> and immortality; eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry puniſhment (as <hi>Tiburtius</hi> faith) being poor, where a good conſcience keeps us company. When we ſhall be freed from this dark <hi>Lant-horn</hi> of fleſh and frailty, and when we ſhall be raiſed from death, we ſhall not grieve ſo much, becauſe the <hi>joyes</hi> of this life were not real, as we ſhall rejoyce, becauſe they were none at all.</p>
            <p>That lump of miſery (holy <hi>Job</hi>) whoſe ſpirit was nothing but patience, as his body was nought but <hi>Sores,</hi> retained alwayes his <hi>Affections</hi> in an equal
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170556:8"/>Reſignation, <hi>Came I naked into of the world? ſo ſhall I go out,</hi> Job 1.21. There is as much valour to be ſhewed in a Bed as in an Army: But alas! though we cannot avoid <hi>Evils,</hi> how are we afraid to bear them!</p>
            <p>Indeed, we interpret out <hi>Afflictions</hi> amiſs, and therefore are caſt down; we take every whipping to be an effect of <hi>Anger,</hi> when it is a ſign of <hi>Love.</hi> God makes us ſick in our body, to cure ſome diſeaſe in our <hi>Soul.</hi> Can we attain to <hi>Tabor,</hi> before we paſs by <hi>Calvary?</hi> Shall we not firſt taſt <hi>Gall</hi> with our Saviour, before we receive the ſweet benefits of his bleſſed <hi>Reſurrection?</hi> Ah! is there any ſuch precious thing to be gotten in the world, that we ſhould forſake Jeſus in the wilderneſs of Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and pleaſe our ſelves in the vain and tranſito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hopes of our own unbridled <hi>Fancies?</hi> How do we know whither in deſiring to be delivered from <hi>Affliction,</hi> we do not ask of God to take away a gift, which is neceſſary to our ſalvation? ſeeing that <hi>Malady,</hi> or Affliction, which makes us di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate worldly pleaſures, gives us a diſpoſition to taſt the joyes of Heaven.</p>
            <p>The brave and happy men of this world enjoy their <hi>wiſhes,</hi> but their <hi>Ship</hi> doth periſh in the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, as it is ſporting; whereas God [by his infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Providence] gives Tempeſts to his <hi>Elect,</hi> that he may work a miraculous <hi>Calm,</hi> by his Almighty Power. And though the waters ſeem to reſerve their choler, to vent it only upon the Ship which carries juſt perſons, yet is it alwayes accompanied with that happy and comfortable voice, <hi>It is I, be not afraid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:170556:9"/>
God takes off his own people from the ilneſs of their wayes, <hi>By hedging them up with Thorns,</hi> Hoſ. 2.6. But it is to bring them into a <hi>Bed of Roſes,</hi> and by the wormwood of this world to ſhew the ſweetneſs of himſelf. He is pleaſed to draw the <hi>Inſtruments</hi> of his <hi>Power</hi> out of the <hi>Objects</hi> of our <hi>Infirmities:</hi> where he comes, the <hi>Tempeſt</hi> ceaſeth; and they know Jeſus very ill, who (with his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples) in the <hi>Storms</hi> of Affliction, take him for an <hi>Illuſion,</hi> and cry out for fear of his preſence, which ſhould make them moſt rejoyce.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Affliction</hi> opens the eyes of man, and makes him come to <hi>himſelf,</hi> that he may the better return to God; and it is a great offence to break that glaſs, which repreſenteth us to our ſelves, by a friendly correction. Why ſhould I be afraid to ſhew my <hi>heart</hi> ſtark naked to him, whoſe <hi>Arrowes</hi> no ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er <hi>pierce,</hi> but heal; who tells us, <hi>Afflictions</hi> and <hi>Scourges</hi> in this life, are like to be our portion. And ſhall we think to ſpeed better then our Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter? who at laſt intends us a Crown, will turn our water into wine; and (according to <hi>Sampſons,</hi> Ridle) <hi>Out of the Eater ſhall come meat, and out of the ſtrong ſweetneſs. David</hi> had forty years <hi>Reign</hi> for ſeven years <hi>Baniſhment:</hi> and <hi>Joſeph</hi> (though thirteen years under a Cloud, through falſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment) reigned fourſcore years a King in <hi>Aegypt.</hi> And ſurely Gods ends are no other, then to wean us from the world, to draw us nearer to himſelf; to humble and to prove us, that he may do us good at the later end, <hi>Deut.</hi> 8.16.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:170556:9"/>
Oh Happy Afflictions to keep the heart plia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and tender towards our God! yea thrice happy is he who can ſay (with the Prophet) <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring mine Affliction, and my miſery; the wormwood and the Gall; my ſoul hath them ſtill in Remembrance, and is humbled in me.</hi> Lam. 3.19, 20. And hence is it that the Apoſtle alſo bids us, <hi>Call to remembrance the former dayes in which after we were illuminated, we endured a great fight of afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: partly whileſt we were made a gazing ſtock both by reproaches and afflictions,</hi> Hebrews 10.32, 33.</p>
            <p>God is thus pleaſed to mind us of the frailty of our condition, ſince when we are in <hi>Proſperity,</hi> we are ready to kick the heel, and forget him. Where did <hi>Adam</hi> take his Fall, but in <hi>Paradice</hi> [the midſt of the Trees of pleaſure?] Where is the poor <hi>Bee</hi> more ſubject to be drowned, then in a Pot of <hi>honey?</hi> Neither are we ever nearer a <hi>Surfeit,</hi> then in the midſt of <hi>Delicacies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We find <hi>Flowers</hi> to be ever ſweeteſt after a Shower, yea to drop the ſweeteſt water, when fire is under them. The Gold loſeth its droſs by refining, and the Corn its Chaffe by the Flail. Who then would not be willing to be under Gods <hi>pruning knife,</hi> that he may bring forth more fruit? <hi>John</hi> 15.2. Who would not be content to ſit (with <hi>Job</hi>) on the <hi>Dung-hill,</hi> bereav'd of all his goods and comforts, when they ſhall be redoubled; yea not only to receive <hi>manifold more in this life, but everlasting life hereafter?</hi> Luk. 18.30. Surely none (me thinks) ſhould repine to drink of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170556:10"/>Chriſts Cup here, ſince at laſt it will be ſweetned with ſuch good Ingredients.</p>
            <p>It was the ſaying of one, that all the pleaſures injoyed by all men of the world, were not worth one hours in Heaven; the thought whereof made that great Marqueſs <hi>Galeaceus Caracciolus</hi> (though rich, and of much eſteem in the world) ſo ſtrongly to with-ſtand thoſe, who tempted him to return to his own Countrey. Alas! (ſaid he) let their riches periſh with them, who eſteem all the gold in the world, worth one dayes ſociety with <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and his holy Spirit!</p>
            <p>Anſwerable whereunto is that ſweet and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly language of the Apoſtle; <hi>I account not</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the Afflictions of this life, worthy to be compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with the glory which ſhall be revealed in us,</hi> Rom. 8.18. Yea, <hi>He eſteemed all things but loſs, for the excellency of Chriſt, for whom he had ſuffered the loſs of all things, accounting them but dung, that he might win Chriſt,</hi> Phil. 3.8. He well knew, that comfort was not the ſtanding diſh of a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> in this life; nor <hi>Cordials</hi> to be fit, but for thoſe that are <hi>fainting.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Raw fleſh (ſaith a Reverend <hi>Biſhop</hi>) is noiſome to the ſtomack, and yields no good nouriſhment be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it be ſodden; ſo are we to God, before we are ſoked and boiled in <hi>Afflictions.</hi> Chriſt died, and bled, and wept for our ſouls, and ſhall not we ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer a little with him, ſince it is eſpecially for our own advantage at laſt? Which of the Saints of the world, was without <hi>Croſses</hi> and Tribulations, and ſhall we think to eſcape that which no man could ever avoid?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:170556:10"/>
The <hi>Diſciple</hi> it ſeems made too much haſt back from the Sepulcher to find <hi>Chriſt,</hi> Joh. 20.10, 11. but <hi>Mary</hi> ſtanding there <hi>weeping,</hi> ſaw her <hi>Saviour.</hi> And certainly, he that ſigheth not here with him, as a <hi>Pilgrim,</hi> ſhall never rejoyce with him here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after as a <hi>Citizen.</hi> Was it not he (our Captain) who ſhew'd us the way? He that could make <hi>Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors</hi> out of thoſe that were <hi>ſpeechleſs,</hi> had nor one word to ſay againſt the <hi>Revilers.</hi> He which could command <hi>Frogs</hi> and <hi>Flies</hi> to overthrow mighty Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, would not have one <hi>Diſciple</hi> to draw his Sword. He that was without ſpot by his unparal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel'd Sufferings, took away our <hi>ſtains,</hi> and through his innocency anvanc'd the Standard of the Croſs. He that was the Fountain of Glory, deſcended to the loweſt abaſements. He that had <hi>life</hi> at com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, was raviſhed by the <hi>Object</hi> of his <hi>death,</hi> and tranſported by the <hi>Idea</hi> of his Sufferings.</p>
            <p>Shall we not then love that <hi>Croſs,</hi> which he hath cheriſhed as his <hi>Spouſe?</hi> Surely, we ſhall never be worthy of him, untill we bear, as well the <hi>Enſigns,</hi> of his War, as the <hi>Ornaments</hi> of his peace.</p>
            <p>Let our care be, that we ſuffer not for <hi>evil doing</hi> which is the way not to carry the Croſs of our Lord, but of the bad <hi>Thief.</hi> Neither-be thou troubled for ſuffering for thy <hi>Innocency,</hi> which is greater honor, then to ſuffer for a direct Offence. Chriſt was not the leſs the King of Heaven, for ſuffering himſelf to be crowned with <hi>Thorns</hi> in this world; nor his Servants the worſe, for the Reproaches of his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, which he long ſince told them they muſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:170556:11"/>
The <hi>Viper</hi> would ſooner light upon St. <hi>Paul,</hi> then the <hi>Barbarian;</hi> Neither do Pirates uſe to ſet upon empty Ships, but purſue thoſe which are richly loa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den. Satan is quiet with thoſe that he hath got in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his poſſeſſion; his Temptations are a ſign that God loves, where he hates; and though he ſhould winnow thee with the <hi>Fan,</hi> and bruiſe thee with the <hi>Flail,</hi> yet thy faith ſhall not fail: but at laſt be ſure the Salt-ſea of thy <hi>Tears</hi> ſhall become a flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing <hi>Field,</hi> as it did to Gods people of old. The <hi>Cloud</hi> which appeared to <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> carried with it ſtorms, and winds, but it was withall incompaſſed with a <hi>golden Circle;</hi> to teach us, that Storms of <hi>Afflictions,</hi> are at laſt accompanied with bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and felicity; and the greateſt loſſes with the beſt advantages.</p>
            <p>Our Saviour choſe the places of delight for ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of pains, and never looked upon thoſe dainty <hi>Sweets,</hi> but to draw out of them moſt bitter <hi>Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows. Gardens</hi> indeed were made for Recreations, but our Saviour there finds only Deſolation; The Plants whereof did groan, the Roſes ſeemed flowers of death, and the Springs belonging to them, fountains of <hi>Tears,</hi> ſweat, and blood. Heaven wore mourning on the Croſs, all the Citizens of heaven wept over his Torments; The Earth qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, the ſtones rent themſelves, Sepulchers open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the dead ariſe; only <hi>Jeſusdies</hi> immovable upon his Thron of patience.</p>
            <p>Who then alas! can chuſe, but be aſtoniſhed at the tranquillity of his Spirit, that amongſt thoſe great <hi>convulſions</hi> of the world, which accompanied
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170556:11"/>him all his life, and moved all about the Croſs at his death: amongſt ſuch bloody dolours, inſolent cries, and unſufferable Blaſphemies [bleeding, weeping, and praying] he ſhould ſhew ſuch a ſereni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Spirit in the very gulf of <hi>Afflictions,</hi> to which all the ſufferings in the world, are but ſo many Flea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitings.</p>
            <p>This (indeed) was that bloody Sacrifice, which hath been expected from all Ages. And what <hi>ſoul</hi> is not raviſhed with admiration, and carried be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond it ſelf, to behold thoſe ſpectacles of horrour, that bottom of endleſs goodneſs and mercy! Its a great way of Remedy, <hi>Similes aliorum reſpice caſus, mitius iſta feres;</hi> to compare our condition with thoſe, whoſe ſufferings we find to be greater.</p>
            <p>And can we think on a deeper <hi>Pattern</hi> of griefes and ſorrow? what though we receive no comfort from the Creature, is it not enough that we have it from the Creator? The infuſion of the leaſt piece of his Croſs [I mean a true intereſt in his merits and <hi>Paſſion</hi>] being able to make the bittereſt afflictions of this world to become ſweet and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant. And can we think on that depth of grieſ and ſorrow his ſoul was in, when he cryed out, <hi>My God! my God! why haſt thou forſaken me?</hi> praying three times, when his ſoul was heavey unto the death, <hi>that the cup might paſs from him;</hi> and ſhall not we ſuffer a little for his ſake?</p>
            <p>Mingle then thy <hi>Sighs</hi> with the ſufferings of thy Saviour; and O what ſweetneſs ſhalt thou find in <hi>Afflictions!</hi> Lay all thy ſortows on him, who was not only the greateſt of <hi>Sufferers,</hi> but is the beſt of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:170556:12"/>
               <hi>Phyſicians.</hi> Caſt thy ſelf at the feet of his mercy, who commanded us to deny our ſelves, ſhewing us the way of taking up our Croſs, and our <hi>Thorns</hi> ſhall then become <hi>Roſes,</hi> in the ſame place where thou haſt <hi>ſighed</hi> ſo much: and out of their ſharpneſs ſhall we compoſe a Crown of <hi>Glory.</hi> Make thy ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities familiar with thee, whereby they will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the leſs troubleſom; avoid the effect, or diſanull the cauſe, with a mature Judgement, and arm thy ſelf againſt all ſuch violent incurſions, as may invade thy mind.</p>
            <p>Thy Saviour wrought out thy ſalvation in an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of <hi>Baſeneſs,</hi> and oughteſt not thou [in thy way to glory] to be conformable to thy head, and paſs through an Eſtate of miſety? we are choſen to a portion of <hi>Afflictions,</hi> as well as to Grace and Glory; <hi>Whoſoever will live godly in Ieſus, muſt ſuffer perſecution;</hi> and therefore to frame a Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that hath no trouble with it, is to frame an <hi>Idol.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Happy ſure are they then, who improve all ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages to advance their chiefeſt good; who la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to grow better by Croſſes, as well as bleſſings, &amp; learn to make a ſanctified uſe of every thing: which I confeſs it is no eaſie thing to fleſh and blood, ſeeing <hi>Religion</hi> is a <hi>Myſtical</hi> and ſpiritual thing, and the <hi>Tenents</hi> thereof ſeem <hi>Paradoxes</hi> to carnal men; as that a <hi>Christian</hi> is the only free man, whileſt other men are ſlaves; that he is the only rich man, though never ſo poor in the world; that he is the only <hi>Beautifull</hi> man, though (outwardly) never ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed; that he is of great <hi>eſteem,</hi> though never ſo much reviled, reproacht and defam'd; and that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170556:12"/>he only is the <hi>happieſt</hi> man, who can rejoyce in the midſt of his miſeries.</p>
            <p>And as <hi>Children</hi> deal with nuts, ſo ſhould wiſe men with <hi>Afflictions,</hi> to break the ſhell, and eat the Kernel. The <hi>Rod</hi> indeed hath a voice, and we ought to hear it; but where God ſtrikes with his <hi>Rod,</hi> he ſupports with his <hi>Staffe.</hi> The Diamond (if intervening the Load-ſtone) hinders its action; ſo the ſweetneſs of <hi>Affliction</hi> (if ſanctified by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor thereof) ſhall work for good (as ſhall all things elſe) to thoſe that fear him. The <hi>Barren</hi> woman wiſheth for the hour of <hi>Child-bearing,</hi> which though painfull, is but ſhort, and afterwards joyfull.</p>
            <p>And is it not very convenient that in this world the <hi>puniſhment</hi> ſhould be greater then the <hi>Reward,</hi> to let us know, that in the other, the Reward ſhall be greater then our <hi>Sufferings.</hi> Never had we been happy, if we had not been miſerable; <hi>Periiſses, niſi periiſſes; had we not been thus ſick, we had died.</hi> Infelicity brings us this happineſs, to make the reſt of our life the <hi>Sweeter,</hi> and our expectation here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after the greater.</p>
            <p>Temptation and miſery is that which only tries a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> (as Sea-men are) in the Tempeſts of this world. <hi>Vulnus non penetrat animam, A wound hurts not the ſoul.</hi> Neither is <hi>Affliction</hi> other then the Croſs, and Hammer to beat <hi>Repentance</hi> the nearer to our heart; it being Gods end [who is the Author of our diſtreſs, and whoſe Almighty power (guided by a moſt wiſe <hi>Providence,</hi> tempered with a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly love, intends nothing at laſt, but what may work for his glory, and our good] thus to deal
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170556:13"/>with us, leſt we ſhould take the place of our <hi>baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> here for our Countrey, and the <hi>Earnest</hi> of our Inheritance for a full <hi>payment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The world (indeed) brings us pleaſures in <hi>golden Cups,</hi> and like the <hi>Strumpet (the wiſe man mentions) whoſe lips drop honey, and whoſe words are ſweeter then oyl, but her feet go down unto death, and many ſtrong men have been ſlain by her,</hi> Pro. 5.3, 5. Our great Adverſary firſt brings us on the <hi>Pinacle</hi> (with our Saviour) promiſing us, all that we can ſee, but all this while takes advantage againſt us. But Gods dealing is otherwiſe, he firſt gives us <hi>Corroſives,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he adminiſter his <hi>Cordials;</hi> he firſt humbles be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he exalts us: untill at laſt, he gives us occaſion to ſay with that princely Prophet, <hi>Thou haſt turned for me my mourning into dancing; thou hast put off my Sack-cloth, and girded me with gladneſſe,</hi> Pſalm 30.11.</p>
            <p>Let Patience then ſo far perfect it ſelf, as to make us willing to look as well upon our Sufferings as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights.</p>
            <p>Uſe renders all things eaſie; and that which in the beginning ſeems full of trouble and affright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, becomes a pleaſure in the end. <hi>Poyſon</hi> kills, and yet how have ſome been nouriſhed thereby? Holy <hi>Job</hi> having encountred with an Army of furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Evils,</hi> and languiſhing upon a <hi>Dung-hill</hi> (the very ſink of corruption and uncleanneſs) under grievous Ulcers and Diſeaſes; and after the loſs of all his Children and ſubſtance, was not at all affright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but played with the <hi>worms,</hi> and made that which his uncharitable friends eſteemed for ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170556:13"/>and miſery, to be his meditation and mirth. While he retained his Integrity, he could not miſs of joy: and though <hi>Corruption</hi> was his <hi>Father,</hi> the <hi>worms</hi> his <hi>mother,</hi> and ſoars had throughout encom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed him, yet through this loathſom <hi>Veil</hi>-ſhin'd the beautifull and healing hand of a <hi>mercifull God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Weak then was that ſaying of <hi>Democritus, It is good to learn what to ſuffer, but not to ſuffer them. Evils</hi> indeed fore-ſeen loſe much of their Edge. But of a more Heroick Temper ſeemed that Speech of <hi>Bion, It is a great evil not to be able to bear Evils;</hi> a good man by his Conflicts being made a Spectacle to the world, to men, and to <hi>Angels,</hi> and by an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>during patience and over-comming ſufferance, not only receives the glorious <hi>Olive Branch,</hi> but wearies the hands of thoſe that beat him.</p>
            <p>One of the <hi>Philoſophers</hi> being highly provoked to impatience; <hi>Ah!</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>vex me as much as thou canſt, thou ſhalt never make me to give thee an ill word.</hi> How wholeſome then is that pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and innocent forbearance which prevents <hi>ſin</hi> and ſorrow [the conſequent of it] whereas it would prove but an ill courſe, <hi>Clavum expellere clavo,</hi> to right one injury by offering another? Revenge ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver conquers malice, which you muſt overcome with goodneſs.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Heathen</hi> could ſay, that the Gods were well pleaſed to ſee good <hi>men</hi> contending with <hi>Adverſity.</hi> Art thou then contemned, rejected, deſpiſed of the world? art thou forſaken of thy friends, &amp; do thy kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred ſtand gazing on thee afar off? yet comfort thy
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170556:14"/>ſelf, go on merrily: as it was ſaid of <hi>Agar</hi> in the wilderneſs, God ſees thee, he takes notice of thee; and as he can relieve, ſo he will (in time) vindicate thee. If thou canſt but find faith to believe it, he will find means to effect it.</p>
            <p>A <hi>Tyrant</hi> (as the Ancients held) was the beſt <hi>Sacrifice</hi> to <hi>Jupiter;</hi> and his beſt <hi>Object</hi> was a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented <hi>mind.</hi> Our Sufferings are but toies, (ſaith <hi>Seneca</hi>) <hi>Behold</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>a Spectacle worthy of God, a man patient, and contented with his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The poor <hi>Sheep</hi> is patient as well when the <hi>Fleece</hi> is ſhorn, as when it groweth upon her back; and ſhall not we be patient, when we meet with <hi>Croſſes,</hi> as well as when we receive <hi>Bleſſings?</hi> Shall we not lay our mouth in the duſt, and be ſilent, when we meet with <hi>evil</hi> from that hand, which makes us to abound with all good, when we injoy all, and when we are ſtript of all. If thou canſt not now indure ſo little, how wilt thou be able to ſuffer <hi>Eternal</hi> Flames hereafter? If a little ſuffering make thee impatient, what will hell fire do in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther world?</p>
            <p>Aſſure thy ſelf, thou ſhalt not have two <hi>Paradiſes.</hi> It is impoſſible to enjoy the delights and pleaſures of the world, and to <hi>Reign</hi> with thy Saviour in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. Now are thy pains profitable, thy tears ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable, and thy ſighs and groans audible; yea a thouſand years of the ſharpeſt pennance here, far leſs then one hours grief hereafter.</p>
            <p>If then the <hi>divine Providence</hi> think it fit, <hi>to write bitter things againſt thee;</hi> if he pleaſe to keep thee
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170556:14"/>from putrefaction, by ſteeping thee in briniſh <hi>Tears</hi> of the <hi>Sea</hi> of this world, be not diſmayed; for how ſhould God wipe away thy Tears in <hi>Heaven,</hi> if on earth thou ſhed them not? or how ſhould heaven be the place of our Reſt, if that on earth we were not troubled?</p>
            <p>He to whom in all our preſſures, dangers, and Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, we ought to have recourſe, and from whoſe hand rewards are to be expected, can turn our <hi>chains</hi> of Iron into ſilver. When St. <hi>Paul</hi> wiſheth much hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs unto <hi>Felix,</hi> he reſerved his Bonds and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonments to himſelf, <hi>Acts</hi> 26.28. Thoſe golden <hi>fetters</hi> he thought too worthy, or elſe a burthen too heavy for <hi>Felix</hi> to undergo.</p>
            <p>Whatſoever falls upon us from the hand of the Almighty, is a <hi>Diamond. Content</hi> [which was Saint <hi>Pauls Elixir</hi>] turns the rudeſt mettal into ſmooth and ductible <hi>gold.</hi> Heaven doth not alwayes own and proſper its own quarrel; but makes our enemies oftentimes to aſſail us hardly; ſeeking in our <hi>loſſes</hi> the revenge of our <hi>ſins,</hi> or increaſe of our patience; &amp; many are the <hi>Ship-wracks</hi> where into the wind of fortunate <hi>Succeſs</hi> would other wayes carry us.</p>
            <p>Neither (ſince proſperous <hi>Victories</hi> (if ill manag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) bring forth more damage with them, then <hi>defeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> do) ſhould we unaviſedly queſtion that <hi>Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi> which watcheth over all our <hi>Deſigns:</hi> there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not more <hi>ſtars</hi> in the firmament, then their are <hi>eyes</hi> over all our <hi>Actions.</hi> And if God ſeem ſometimes to ſleep in the midſt of our miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, it is to the end to ſave us with more wonder, &amp; make more evident Taſtimonies of his love, ſnrely
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170556:15"/>
               <hi>Innocence</hi> is not alwayes a ſhelter; the vertuous of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten die with <hi>thirſt,</hi> whileſt others more undeſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, ſurfeit with earthly bleſſings, and as well abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the benefits, as provoking the Juſtice of their Creator.</p>
            <p>A day will come, which will put our condition in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a better fortune: God only for a time ſhewing himſelf with the malice of the wicked, as we uſe to deal with <hi>Serpents,</hi> from whom we take their <hi>venome,</hi> and cruſh their heads. He can make the fleſh of <hi>Vipers</hi> to aſſiſt in <hi>Cordials;</hi> he can make our <hi>weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes</hi> alſo to be ſtrength only for a time: he puts his marks upon us, leſt we ſhould ſtraggle from him.</p>
            <p>The <hi>heats</hi> of Affliction are but the chafing of the <hi>Wax,</hi> to ſeal us to him. Theſe <hi>Spots</hi> are but the <hi>Letters</hi> wherein he writes his own <hi>Name,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyes himſelf unto us. If he pleaſe to ſend us <hi>Sickneſs,</hi> let us eſteem our ſpiritual health before that of the body. It was St. <hi>Johns</hi> wiſh, <hi>That</hi> Gaius <hi>might proſper in health, even as his ſoul proſpers.</hi> For if the ſoul be lean, the body is amiſs, and if the <hi>Soul</hi> wither, the verdure of the body is but an <hi>Illuſion,</hi> and the godlieſt man but a fearfull <hi>Ghoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is this thy body then wearied with <hi>Afflictions?</hi> No matter, ſo thy ſoul be at peacefull <hi>Reſt.</hi> The <hi>Spouſe</hi> ſaid, <hi>I ſleep, but my ſoul waketh.</hi> The <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent is no way able</hi> to loſe his joy, neither the guilty able to receive any Comfort. If thy courſe <hi>Robes</hi> trouble thee, remember the ſwadling <hi>Cloths</hi> of thy <hi>Saviour.</hi> If thy <hi>Bed</hi> uneafie, yet it is not worſe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170556:15"/>then his <hi>Manger.</hi> And yet [beſides all this] he ſuffered all the pains and forrows which we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved.</p>
            <p>Expect not then to be more gently treated, then the beſt and wiſeſt of men, then the Apoſtles and Saints, nay, then the Son of the Eternal God, the <hi>Heir</hi> of both the worlds, and the Lord of men and Angels, who was alſo the King of <hi>Sufferings.</hi> But all this being well conſidered, thou haſt great reaſon to ſit down, and warm thy ſelf by thy own fire; and feed upon content at home, when thy little misfortune troubles thee.</p>
            <p>And this thou ſhalt the more eaſily do: if thou ſurvey all the <hi>States</hi> and Families of the world, and if thou enlarge thy thoughts, by thinking, how that in the moſt beauteous and ſplendid <hi>Fortune,</hi> ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny cares and interruptions are to be found: and that however Poverty and hardſhips faſten not on the <hi>Favourites</hi> thereof, yet <hi>Sickneſs</hi> and innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>Cares</hi> are ſtill at their heels: yea, the chief Prince or Protector of a Nation, ſits often times upon a <hi>Tribunal</hi> with great <hi>Ceremony</hi> and oſtentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and yet ſomething in his <hi>Breaſt</hi> cauſeth him to ſigh deeply.</p>
            <p>But methinks, I hear thee ſay, is the <hi>Glory</hi> of heaven no perfecter in it ſelf, but that it needs a foil of <hi>Depreſſion</hi> and Ingloriouſneſs to ſet it forth in this world? Is the joy of heaven no perfecter in it ſelf, but that it needs the ſowerneſs of this life to give it a taſt? No ſurely, this is the courſe which thoſe glorious ſouls which now inhabit <hi>Eternity,</hi> have taken. <hi>Tum maxime cum novitas excitat pala
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170556:16"/>Thoſe things taſt ſweeteſt which are ſtained with moſt coſt and difficulty.</hi> Never is the corn more clean, then when it hath paſt the <hi>Flail;</hi> never is gold more approved, then when it comes from the Touch-ſtone.</p>
            <p>It is reported of <hi>Alexander</hi> the <hi>Phyſician,</hi> that he would have <hi>Lapis Lazuli</hi> fifty times waſhed, before it were uſed; and it is the Will of the great <hi>Phyſician</hi> of our ſouls, to have us often tried in the <hi>fire</hi> of <hi>Affliction;</hi> and to taſt that honey, which proceeds only from bitter hearbs. That <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dial</hi> which ſucceeds an unpleaſant <hi>Potion,</hi> muſt needs be welcome to fainting a ſoul.</p>
            <p>And as a help hereunto, we have the <hi>Example</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Apostles;</hi> of <hi>Moſes</hi> and all the wiſe men of all Ages of the world; who (well underſtanding how to diſtinguiſh <hi>good</hi> from <hi>evil</hi>) did for a ſhort time here, chuſe a ſad and melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly way to <hi>Felicity,</hi> rather then the broad, pleaſant, and eaſie way to <hi>miſery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither may we expect all fair dayes here, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome clouds, and the taſt of the bitter waters of this world. Thou muſt ſometimes ſit mourning with the <hi>Pelican;</hi> thy beauty muſt be ſtrewed with <hi>Aſhes,</hi> and ſpend ſome time in ſolitude and darkneſs, in putting off all our <hi>gorgious Ornaments,</hi> and putting on <hi>Sack-cloth;</hi> in eating the bread of ſorrow; in lying in the duſt, in weeping, in faſting, in kneeling and praying, in ſmiting the <hi>Breaſt,</hi> and in proſtrating our ſelves to the ground, to wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come thoſe who have undertaken the profeſſion of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:170556:16"/>
Where ſhouldſt thou expect to find thy Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, but on the <hi>Croſs;</hi> and in what poſture wouldſt thou rather have him to find thee then in ſighing and groaning; in lifting up of eyes and hands to heaven; in fervency of prayer [the devouteſt temper of the ſoul] and in an humble, penitent, contrite and broken heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs?</p>
            <p>After which gloomy <hi>Night</hi> of ſorrow, the chearfull and refreſhing <hi>day-light,</hi> will be the more welcome. If <hi>Ieſus</hi> be thy Phyſician, its no matter how long thou art ſick: no matter if thou canſt ſay (with <hi>Jacob</hi>) he is in thy <hi>Affti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> though thou ſee him not. What though our <hi>Bones</hi> are parched, and our moiſture con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed <hi>through our daily complaining,</hi> ſhall we (with <hi>Hagar</hi>) cry out for water, when we are neareſt the <hi>Fountain?</hi> or ſhall we fear drowning whilſt Chriſt is in the Ship, though he ſeem a ſleep?</p>
            <p>For though God be pleaſed thus to bring his <hi>Children</hi> on their knees, and to wring from them the penitent <hi>Tears</hi> of confeſſion, yet doth he well know how to withdraw his heavy yoak, and after the loweſt <hi>Ebb</hi> of ſorrow, to ſend us the higheſt <hi>Spring</hi> of comfort.</p>
            <p>The <hi>ſoul</hi> of every Saint conſiſts of <hi>ſacred Riddles</hi> and <hi>holy Contradictions;</hi> ſometimes rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to ſink with grief; then again, lifted up with <hi>joy.</hi> Sometimes (with <hi>Job</hi>) ſitting in the duſt, and complaining, <hi>Why he was made a mark to ſhoot at,</hi> but preſently is aſſured, <hi>That his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170556:17"/>lives, and that he ſhall again ſee God.</hi> Sometimes (with <hi>David</hi>) he ſits on the houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>top, like a ſparrow, <hi>mourning like a Dove, and chattering like a Crane.</hi> Then again, <hi>Singing and making melody in his heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh happy <hi>Storm,</hi> which can thus bring us from the <hi>waters</hi> of <hi>Babylon</hi> into ſo joyfull a <hi>Calm!</hi> who would not for a time endure <hi>Hell</hi> to injoy <hi>Heaven?</hi> Hadſt thou <hi>not been afflicted, thou hadſt gone a ſtray.</hi> Ah how pleaſantly wouldſt thou have ſung a <hi>Requiem</hi> to thy ſick <hi>Soul?</hi> How ſecurely miſcarried with a fair wind? and how ſweetly have periſhed in thy ſins, had not the breath of Gods anger a little ſtopt thee? who croſſeth thee in thy <hi>expectation,</hi> whereby to bind thee faſter to himſelf, and reſpects thy good more then thy appetite.</p>
            <p>Alas! This world is not ſtrew'd with <hi>Roſes,</hi> neither have we any ſurer way to reach to <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> then by a crown of <hi>Thorns;</hi> or to receive the honour of the day, then by enduring the heat thereof. It is a ſaying that <hi>Iamblichus</hi> cites out of <hi>Pythagoras, That every good thing conſiſts of ſubſtance and uſe, and not of meer knowledge.</hi> Learned <hi>Aphoriſms</hi> heal not the diſeaſed, but bitter <hi>medicines.</hi> A skilfull Phyſician profits not the ſick, unleſs he falls to practiſe; nor is that ſoul ſaved, which can reaſon <hi>ſubtily,</hi> and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe <hi>elegantly,</hi> but doth no good <hi>works.</hi> Thoſe only that bring their Talents home with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, ſhall be made <hi>Rulers</hi> over <hi>Cities.</hi> And who more fit to receive a <hi>Reward,</hi> then he that hath run hardeſt for it?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:170556:17"/>
Had we not been told by the words of <hi>Truth,</hi> that all things have the like event here on earth, <hi>Eccles.</hi> 2.15. and that the beſt may ſuffer as well as the worſt [thoug <hi>Afflictions</hi> to the one, are <hi>tryals,</hi> to the other puniſhments] we had ſome cauſe to droop and hang down our heads: But ſince true piety [though the beſt policy] is not alwayes attended with <hi>Proſperity,</hi> we may ſafely conclude, that no Magician or Sooth-ſayer, no Aſtrologer or Enchanter, ſhall be able to ſpell any ſuch meaning [as to Gods diſpleaſure] out of that hand-writing which ſeems to be directed againſt thoſe, who (through the heavy loads of <hi>Afflictions</hi> ſeem to be forſaken of God, as well as of man) Why are we troubled? why are we caſt down?</p>
            <p>Did we not know that all the felicity of <hi>man</hi> in this world is a dream, (it comes on we know not how; and when it vaniſheth, we cannot ſo much as diſcern, whether it is gone; that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever in this world we call <hi>fruition,</hi> is but <hi>Face-acquaintance,</hi> and all temporal poſſeſſions, but a looking on) we might in ſome caſe, have cauſe of ſorrow: But ſince all things paſs away in an unperceived motion; and when we ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe our beſt enjoyments to be faſt lockt in our <hi>Armes,</hi> they creep from us in a miſt or ſmoak, (which ſteals out at the Chimney-top, after it hath fouled it within) why do we ſigh, and groan, and moan, and ſink under the burthen of what will one day lead us to an incomparable weight of Glory? 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17, 18.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:170556:18"/>
Were not <hi>Suffering</hi> of the firſt <hi>Statutes</hi> of the great <hi>Magna Charta</hi> in Heaven, and will ſurely find us out, whether we be born in <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> or under the Spiders Web; inhabit we Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laces, or live in Cottages, we might (like that poor <hi>flower</hi> (which ſhuts it ſelf at the Suns ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence) ſit down, and weep under a cloud of ſorrow. But ſeeing the ſupream and eternal <hi>Wiſdom</hi> [which is the Maſter and Deviſer of this worldly <hi>Drama</hi>] aſſigns us our parts as well of ſuffering as pleaſure; Why ſhould we mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mure? Why do we repine?</p>
            <p>May we conſider further, that the life of man is a mavrelous <hi>Comody,</hi> wherein the greateſt part of our <hi>Actions</hi> are plaid under a <hi>Curtain.</hi> The <hi>rich</hi> man and the <hi>poor</hi> meet in this world; the one abounding in Treaſure; the other lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with miſeries and <hi>Ulcers;</hi> though their <hi>Ends</hi> are often as different, as their lives are contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, the one falling into a Gulf of fire, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into an <hi>Abyſs</hi> of delights; which ſhould keep us as from repining at the hand of a merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full God, ſo from raſh cenſuring of ſuch as are in extremity: as if God had forgotten them in a time, which he chooſeth purpoſely for the ſhewing of his ſpecial Mercy.</p>
            <p>But here mayſt thou ask me, Why then is man [the only Creature intended to happineſs] thus <hi>born to trouble, as the ſparks flie upwards?</hi> Why through the houſe of Tears he thus travels to the Manſion of joy? or why he alone [being capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of <hi>Beatitude</hi>] is thus made ſubject to miſery?
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170556:18"/>I anſwer, Becauſe he is born for <hi>vertue,</hi> the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dieſt way to attain <hi>Eternity.</hi> He attributeth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that is good to any thing here below, but wholly referreth it to God, from whom (as from the <hi>fountain</hi>) all things proceed.</p>
            <p>And though it may ſeem a <hi>Paradox</hi> (though true in <hi>Phyloſophy</hi>) <hi>That no man is rich, but he that is poor, according to the common account;</hi> yet no wiſe man did ever deſcribe felicity without <hi>vertue;</hi> or true happineſs, without being at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with ſuch Afflictions, as direct us in the wayes of <hi>holineſs;</hi> it being no evil to be wretched, but to be vicious and impatient; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther may we think, that <hi>vertue</hi> depends wholly on <hi>Proſperity</hi> and a god fortune.</p>
            <p>Indeed to thoſe who know not their Saviour, nor meditate how far he hath got the victory, and taken away the ſting of ſuffering (yea of death it ſelf) as their life cannot be pleaſant, ſo their ſufferings can no way be comfortable; they are the moſt unwelcom Meſſengers that ever knockt at their doores: and not only make a <hi>Belſhazar</hi> to tremble, but a <hi>Saul</hi> to fall proſtrate on the Earth, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 28.28. Yea, ſuch black clouds of <hi>ſorrow</hi> many times overtake us, as that (with <hi>Jacob</hi>) we often rend our cloths, <hi>and will needs (with grief) go down into our Graves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But our only wiſe <hi>Phyſician</hi> well knows, that to find out either our <hi>Diſtempers,</hi> or our <hi>Cures,</hi> and to diſcern al the ſad <hi>omens</hi> of our <hi>Afflictions,</hi> and all the prodigious <hi>cauſes</hi> of our <hi>troubles</hi> and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170556:19"/>miſeries, we muſt ſearch deeper then the skin, and ſuperficies of our maladies; the poiſons of malignity of our Nature, being not only deeply diffuſed, but reaching to the very heart, and hidden in the moſt retired <hi>Cells</hi> of our <hi>Souls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alas! We have but one life, and we ſee a thouſand inſtruments of <hi>death,</hi> ready to take it away, and to let out our innocent ſouls; We have but a little breath, and how quickly is it gone? O God, thy firſt breath breath'd a ſoul into me, and ſhall thy breath ſo ſoon blow it out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, through lodes of troubles? I ſee thy <hi>hand</hi> upon me, but I dare not ask thee why it comes, or what it intends? whether thou wilt bid me ſtay longer in this body, or bid me meet thee this day in <hi>paradice:</hi> only makeme willing at all times [Jeſus himſelf having made the way, and gone before] to pay my homage, and drive on with comfort (no way daunted with the ſtorms of a weariſom life) towards thoſe joyes which will at laſt lead me into unſpeakable liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
            <p>Let me ſtill bleſs thee for that <hi>Affliction</hi> which thus ſpeaks nothing but <hi>mercy.</hi> Let me hear thy voice thus calling unto me: I muſt correct thee, but I will not hurt thee; my hand ſhall lie gent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon thee: with gracious reſpites will I viſit thee. If I ſend thee <hi>Croſſes,</hi> I will give thee patience; if I viſit thee with Afflictions, I will give thee a willing ſubmiſſion, and a readineſs to kiſs the <hi>Rod,</hi> and the hand that holds it, yea,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:170556:19"/>a conſtant dependance on that <hi>Arm,</hi> which makes thee ſmart.</p>
            <p>O God! Let me ever thus feel thy <hi>Rod,</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then loſe thy <hi>Affliction!</hi> the plain ſenſe of our ſuffering is, that thou maiſt bring us to Repentance. It is not to conſume our pure <hi>gold,</hi> but to refine us from that droſs, we have [as men] contracted. It is but to open our eyes that we may the better return to him who ſeems ſometimes to withdraw his comforts. Though the Nurſe be often withdrawn, the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to win the <hi>Childs affection:</hi> and the Sun of <hi>Righteouſneſſe</hi> not ſeen of us, though bright (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hynd the clouds of Tryals and Temptations) yet at laſt how doth our barrenneſs yield a plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull Harveſt? And as the Sun-ſhine of Gods countenance, doth ripen our <hi>Graces,</hi> ſo doth cloudy weather advantage their growth in <hi>humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, mourning and ſelf-denial.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And it is no ſmall mercy from God, that in our journey to <hi>Canaan,</hi> we paſs through the wilderneſs of this worlds temptations, and in the way to <hi>Zion,</hi> we paſs through the valley of <hi>Baca:</hi> whilſt we have Chriſt as a cloud and pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar to direct us: God is not tied alwayes to bring is to heaven by one and the ſame <hi>road;</hi> neither is it any matter, if in ſtead of <hi>Jacobs</hi> Ladder, ye are tranſported thither in <hi>Eliahs</hi> fiery Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iot, it being the goodneſs of God to give us patience, courage and conſtancy [which are our higheſt conformity to Chriſt our Saviour] to attend his help, though in the laſt and darkeſt
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170556:20"/>
               <hi>watch</hi> of the night; his relief coming in the beſt time.</p>
            <p>As <hi>Stars</hi> appear brigheſt at <hi>Noon-day</hi> to thoſe who (with <hi>Joſeph</hi>) are in deep pits: ſo divine <hi>Providence</hi> appears <hi>lighteſt</hi> to thoſe who are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitated to make a cordial of the poiſon of the worlds contempts and reproaches. The Royal Title over our Saviours head, was never more glorious, and deſerved, then when he was hanging upon the <hi>Croſs;</hi> ſeeing on that [as a King on his Throne] he moſt conquered both over his, and his Churches enemies. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther were his ſufferings the leaſt of his <hi>ſolemnities</hi> and glories; his Father being never better pleaſed with him, then when he cryed out, <hi>my God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither is it any Argument, that becauſe God puniſheth out faults, he hates our perſons; whoſe Rod and ſtaffe lifted up againſt us, is not to drive us from him, but as a <hi>Shepherds</hi> Crook, to draw us nearer to him, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 23. Though thoſe (indeed) that are ſtrangers to the Croſs of Chriſt, and underſtand not the Afflictions of Chriſtians to be as myſterious as their faith, ſuppoſe they muſt needs be <hi>Murtherers,</hi> on whoſe hands they ſee ſuch <hi>Vipers</hi> hanging, <hi>Acts</hi> 28.4. and no way conſidering, that God ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times loves moſt, where he moſt rebukes; and that they have often times moſt of his heart, from whom he moſt hides his face [as to tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral proſperity and on whom his hand lies heavieſt, as to viſible chaſtiſements, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.5.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:170556:20"/>
He takes the ſafeſt courſe with his Children; that they may not be condemned with the world, he makes the world to condemn them; that they may not love the world, he makes the world to hate them; and that they may be crucified to the world, he makes the world to be crucified to them.</p>
            <p>And hence it is that they meet with croſſes, and abuſes, and wrongs in the world, becauſe God will not have them periſh with the world.</p>
            <p>In this way of Affliction it is, that God doth chiefly manifeſt himſelf to our ſoul; hereby the ſoul unites it ſelf moſt to Chriſt; whereas in times of <hi>Proſperity</hi> it ſcatters and looſeth it ſelf in the Creature, there being an uniting power in Afflictions to make the ſoul gather it ſelf to God.</p>
            <p>The bittereſt things in <hi>religion</hi> are ſweet. And as Gods children are ſtrengthned, and learn to ſtand by their falls; ſo (like tall <hi>Cedars</hi>) the more they are blown, the deeper they are root<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and after all outward ſtorms and inward de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinings, this is the iſſue, <hi>They take root down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and bring footh fruit upwards.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſince there is nothing of God which can pleaſe the world, this ſhould make us to quiet our hearts in the midſt of its unwelcome and tempeſtuous ſtorms, &amp; to account it a greater fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour from God, when the <hi>Michals</hi> of the world ſcoff at us; for when they are offended at us, God is delighted with us; yea, happy are thoſe, who find themſelves amended by thoſe bitter
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:170556:21"/>
               <hi>potions</hi> which [in bad times and by evil men] a good God adminiſters to us for our health; and whereby he intends better to improve us to his ſervice; when (coming out of this fiery Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance) we ſhall ſhine more bright, then ever we did with the love of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What if ſome men fancy to themſelves a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, firſt to mock us, and after to nail us to the Croſs? What though they ſtick not (amidſt our many <hi>Agonies</hi>) to give us gall and vinegar to drink, to load us with cruel contempts, and virulent ſpeeches, and ſcandalous reproaches? What if our <hi>Enemies</hi> walk with haughty looks, triumphant ſpirits, and threatning eyes, whilſt we are full of tears, ſighs and ſorrows? What if falſe witneſſes ariſe, and <hi>lay to our charge things that we never knew, rewarding us evil for good, and hatred for our good will?</hi> What though we are put to pains in our profeſſion, to troubles for a good conſcience, and to many hardſhips in the world? Yet, O let us labour for contentment, becauſe otherwiſe we can no way be made con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable unto Chriſt our Saviour.</p>
            <p>Neither is it any matter if proud and merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs men mingle their ſcornfull <hi>ſmiles</hi> with our Tears. It is no matter if <hi>Davids</hi> Abjects make mouths, and wag their heads upon us; If the great Favourites of the world curſe us, ſo long as God pities us in all our troubles; who will not ſtay too long, leſt we put forth our hand unto wickedneſs. Neither <hi>ſuffer the rod of the wicked to remain alwayes on the lot of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,</hi> Pſal. 125.3.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:170556:21"/>
               <hi>Jobs</hi> miſery did not leſſen his <hi>innocency:</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are the ſervants of the moſt high God troubled, though they are judged here, ſo as they may not be condemed with the world; they triumph in their <hi>ſufferings,</hi> they dance in their <hi>duſt;</hi> yea, they account their <hi>aſhes</hi> their <hi>beauty,</hi> and the waters of <hi>Marah</hi> to be their wine and refreſhing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Affliction</hi> is part of Cods <hi>husbandry,</hi> and tends no leſs to the amendment of our ſouls, then manuring doth to the advantage of the earth? And may we ſtill humble our ſelves as well in ſubmiſſion to, as the acknowledgement of his divine and afflicting hand. And, Oh, that we could hide and abhor our ſelves in duſt and aſhes before his preſence, who only can pity and repair us!</p>
            <p>But miſerable and unhappy are thoſe who (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſo much ſharp eye-ſalve) ſee not their need of a <hi>Phyſician!</hi> for after the long applications of ſuch rough medicines which the world af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords, not to own their diſtempers, were (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed) a contempt to the wiſeſt and gentleſt <hi>Phyſician;</hi> whoſe Judgements are mercifull, and whoſe ſeverities only the fruits of his lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving kindneſs, that he chuſeth rather to puniſh us, then to deſtroy and forſake us.</p>
            <p>A Chriſtian is here in his <hi>Nonage,</hi> and no way fit to have all he hath a <hi>title</hi> to; yet why ſhould he murmure, ſeeing ſo much is alotted him, as will give him paſſage to heaven? if Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty be good, he ſhall have it; if diſgrace be
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170556:22"/>good, he ſhall meet with it; if <hi>Croſſes</hi> be good, he ſhall have them; if miſery be good, it ſhall follow him; yet all tending towards his good. If he be in want, he hath contentment; if un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>ſuffering,</hi> he hath <hi>patience;</hi> all things are his, as well what he wants, as what he hath.</p>
            <p>It is the deſire (indeed) of many men, to be in <hi>Canaan</hi> as ſoon as they are out of <hi>Aegypt:</hi> but God will lead us through the wilderneſs of Temptations and Afflictions, untill we come to Heaven. As the Spring follows the winter, ſo will glory follow our Affliction, which is <hi>hid with Chriſt;</hi> and though now clouded with the <hi>malice</hi> of wicked men, and our own infirmities, we ſhall (at laſt) appear glorious in the eyes of God, and his Angels, if in a Chriſtian meekneſs, we ſubmit to his Will.</p>
            <p>The which ſhould ſerve to comfort us whileſt we remain in this unfortunate <hi>region</hi> [this land of blackneſs] wherein the Inhabitants ſit in the ſhadow of death, and a thick darkneſs [for a time] obſcures the glorious <hi>Sun-ſhine</hi> of all our comforts; and ſuch calamities accompany ſome, as that [between fear of death and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of life] <hi>Vivere noluerit, mori neſcierit; To live he would not, to die he cannot.</hi> And ſurely he cannot be of fleſh, who is unſenſible of what wrings ſo many true Tears from our eyes, and ſo many Icie ſighs of grief and ſorrow from our heart.</p>
            <p>The neceſſity alſo thereof ſhould invite us to patience; all the Saints of God having paſſed
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170556:22"/>and profited thereby; and ſeeing by thoſe Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions [which are no leſs profitable then grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous and troubleſome] we are humbled, purged and inſtructed; and there is no life ſo holy, nor place ſo ſecret, wherein they may be avoided, Oh grudge not then to <hi>ſow in Tears, ſince thou ſhalt reap in joy!</hi> By flight thou canſt not over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, but by patience thou wilt be ſtronger then all thy enemies.</p>
            <p>It is no great matter for a man to be devout and fervent, when he feeleth no heavineſs, but by <hi>Chaſtiſements</hi> he is tryed how much he hath profited in Gods School; whereas our Reward will be the greater, ſo our vertues will more o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly appear to the world, and by the ſharpneſs of our Tryal, our good deeds will be the more eſteemed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Adverſity</hi> diſcovereth how much vertue each one hath: It maketh us not frail, but ſhews us what we are. And God takes away the <hi>bladders</hi> of this world that we may learn to ſwim without them. Such as he moſt loves, he uſeth to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke and chaſten, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.19. Our comfort is, that all our Troubles are determined by the wiſe Counſel and providence of God for our good, yea as bleſſings to us, and ſhal increaſe our Crown of Glory. The deeper our die is in <hi>Affliction,</hi> the better ſhall we wear our ſcarlet <hi>Robes</hi> in Heaven.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lazarus</hi> was not bad enough for Chriſt to cure, whileſt he was ſick, who intended to revive him from death, to make the glory of the Miracle the greater. Neither are we fit <hi>Objects</hi> for our
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:170556:23"/>Saviour to delight in, while we are ſick with the vanities of the world, untill we are mortified with <hi>Afflictions</hi> from above. Surely had there been any better, or more profitable way for the health of man then ſuffering, Chriſt would have ſhewed it by <hi>Word</hi> or <hi>Example:</hi> who plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exhorteth all thoſe that follow him, to the bearing of his Croſs.</p>
            <p>Oh happy Burthen! which we ſhall [at laſt] put off with Eternal comfort! ſtrike on then thy mercifull rod, O God! which thou ſendeſt [not to procure our ſports, yet theſe thou proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peredſt to thy ſervant <hi>Jacob,</hi> but] to work the dicovery of our wounds, by the humble mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation of our ſins unto thee.</p>
            <p>And Oh, that we could but mak a wiſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of our Croſſes, whereby to have recourſe to vertue, to God, and our ſelves! In all worldly mutations, let us acknowledge and kiſs the <hi>divine hand;</hi> let us not fear to walk in that way which lead to a Kingdom. If thou bear thy <hi>Croſs</hi> unwillingly, thou increaſeſt thy load, and makeſt for thy ſelf a new burthen. But if thou bear it willingly, it will bear thee, and lead thee to thy deſired end, to wit, where there ſhall be an end of ſuffering [which here there ſhall not] and where there ſhall be an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting reward laid up for thoſe that <hi>fight the good fight of faith.</hi> If that <hi>Farmer</hi> who gave <hi>Ataxerexes</hi> a diſh of cold water, was rewarded with a golden <hi>Goblet,</hi> how much more likely are they to receive a <hi>Crown, who have denied
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170556:23"/>themſelves, taken up their Croſs, and followed their Maſter?</hi> Be ſure as the glory is his, ſo ſhall the Reward be eternally thine.</p>
            <p>Oh here, here will be a certain Harbor and receſs from all the temptations of the world, and from all the clamours and reproaches of our enemies! In this <hi>Ark</hi> ſhall we cut through all the waves of this troubleſome life, without detriment or putrefaction; in this withdrawing Room (though too ſeldom frequented) ſhines that happy ſtar which will lead us to the King of life.</p>
            <p>Here (by having recourſe to the ſpring of life) may we ſweetly bath and refreſh our wearied <hi>ſouls.</hi> Near this white, may we ſtand ſecure; and having paſſed the rough and unpleaſant Mountains of this world; having ſat down un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der its troubles, and ſpent our breath with much gaſping and wearineſs, on this Hill may we feed our eyes with the beautifull <hi>Proſpect</hi> and freſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of theſe eternally green and flowery <hi>Plains.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:170556:24"/>
            <head>The meaning of the <hi>FRONTISPIECE.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>SIck <hi>with a</hi> holy Love, <hi>the</hi> Soul Divine,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Spurning at</hi> Earth, Heaven <hi>onely ſeeks to clime,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Whilſt</hi> Mary [<hi>full of</hi> Sighs <hi>and</hi> Tears] <hi>doth weep</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Large</hi> Streams, <hi>to waſh her bleſſed</hi> Saviours <hi>feet:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And ſcorning</hi> her <hi>fond</hi> Lovers, <hi>leaves to</hi> ſin,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Returns her</hi> Love-Tokens, <hi>and follows</hi> him.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Behold</hi> one <hi>in a</hi> Wood, <hi>whoſe</hi> life <hi>is ſpent</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In true</hi> Devotion <hi>and</hi> retirement.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Chaſt</hi> Joſeph <hi>ſhuns his</hi> Miſtriſs's Lures <hi>to</hi> ſin,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nor will betray the</hi> Truſt <hi>repos'd in</hi> him.</l>
               <l>Beauty <hi>in one hand, ſhews</hi> Enticements <hi>fair,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The</hi> other <hi>points at</hi> Darts, Chains, Swords, <hi>Deſpair:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>When</hi> treacherous Delilah <hi>had</hi> Sampſon <hi>bound,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The</hi> Houſe <hi>he forthwith level'd with the ground,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Laughing <hi>her friends to</hi> death; <hi>Ah life miſpent!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Murthered <hi>with that, which ſeems our</hi> Merriment;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Next on a wretched</hi> Object, <hi>caſt thine</hi> eyes,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Who with deep</hi> ſighs, <hi>wring'd</hi> hands <hi>&amp; mournful</hi> cryes,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bewailes</hi> Loves <hi>treacherous</hi> Engines. <hi>All which prove</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The</hi> miſery <hi>of</hi> him, <hi>that's tied to</hi> Love:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thoſe that reach</hi> Heaven, <hi>onely being</hi> bleſt,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Though of the worlds</hi> Enjoyments <hi>diſpoſſeſt.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
